地          球          脉          动
100年前
A hundred years ago
地球上生活着15亿人
there were one and a half billion people on Earth.
如今 已有超过60亿人拥挤在 我们这颗脆弱的星球上
Now, over six billion crowd our fragile planet.
尽管如此 地球上仍有一些 人类极少涉足的地方
But even so, there are still places barely touched by humanity.
这部专题片将把你带到最后的蛮荒之地
This series will take to the last wildernesses
展示这个星球的风貌 和你以前从未见过的野生动物
and show you the planet and its wildlife as you have never seen them before.
两        极        之        间
画 外 音
大卫 · 爱登堡   爵士
想象一下一个没有太阳的世界
Imagine our world without sun.
雄帝企鹅正在挑战地球上最严酷的环境
Male Emperor Penguins are facing the nearest that exists on planet Earth -
南极洲的冬天
winter in Antarctica.
黑夜漫无休止
It's continuously dark
气温下降到零下70℃
and temperatures drop to minus seventy degrees centigrade.
其它动物早已逃离 只有企鹅留了下来
The penguins stay when all other creatures have fled
因为每只企鹅都护卫着一件宝贝
because each guards a treasure:
一颗躺在它们脚背上的蛋
a single egg rested on the top of its feet
依靠耷拉下来的肚皮上的绒毛保持温暖
and kept warm beneath the downy bulge of its stomach.
它们没有食物 也没有水
There is no food and no water for them,
而且整整4个月见不到太阳
and they will not see the sun again for four months.
这绝对是动物们经受过的最严酷的考验
Surely no greater ordeal is faced by any animal.
太阳已远离南极
As the sun departs from the Antarctic
照耀在遥远的北方天空
it lightens the skies in the far north.
现在是三月
It's March
阳光重返北极腹地
and light returns to the high Arctic,
驱走了4个月的黑暗
sweeping away four months of darkness.
一只北极熊苏醒了
A polar bear stirs.
整个冬天 它都在洞穴里度过
She has been in her den the whole winter.
它的出现标志着春天的到来
Her emergence marks the beginning of spring.
长达数月的地下闭居已经结束
After months of confinement underground
它从斜坡上一滑而下
she toboggans down the slope.
也许是为了清洁皮毛
Perhaps to clean her fur,
也许只是因为高兴
perhaps for sheer joy.
它的幼熊们第一次注视着 这个明亮的新世界
Her cubs gaze out of their bright new world for the very first time.
母熊召唤着熊崽
The female calls them,
但在这个陡峭的斜坡上 踏出第一步可不太容易
but this steep slope is not the easiest place to take your first steps.
可是它们太饿了
But they are hungry
急切盼着来到母亲身旁
and eager to reach their mother,
在这个特别的日子里  母熊已经推迟了喂奶的时间
who's delayed feeding them on this special day.
现在该是履行承诺的时候了  乳汁是巨大的诱惑
Now she lures them with the promise of milk,
自从熊崽们两个多月前又聋又瞎地 在雪下出生以来 母乳就是它们唯一的食物
the only food the cubs have known since they were born deaf and blind beneath the snow some two months ago.
它们的母亲已有5个月没有进食了
Their mother has not eaten for five months
失去了一半的体重
and has lost half her body weight.
现在它将仅剩的一点脂肪 变成乳汁喂养它的宝贝们
Now she converts the last of her fat reserves into milk for her cubs.
春天的太阳带来了温暖
The spring sun brings warmth
但对母熊而言却是一个问题
but also a problem for the mother.
海面的冰层开始融化
It starts to melt the sea ice.
而母熊则需要在那里捕杀海豹 喂养幼熊
That is where she hunts for the seal she needs to feed her cubs.
因此它必须在冰层破碎之前到达那里
And she must get there before the ice breaks up.
而现在的气温仍然有-30℃
For now though it's still minus thirty degrees
熊崽们必须回到洞中避寒
and the cubs must have the shelter of the den.
现在是北极熊现身后的第6天
It's six days since the bears emerged
春色匆匆
and spring is advancing rapidly.
但即使是现在 暴风雪 仍会在毫无征兆的情况下来袭
But even now blizzards can strike without warning.
幼小的熊崽很容易冻僵  躲在洞穴中可能会更舒服些
Being so small, the cubs are easily chilled and they will be more comfortable resting in the den.
可是母熊必须得把它们带到外边活动
But their mother must keep them out and active.
饥饿将它折磨得虚弱不堪
She's becoming weak from hunger
而这片产仔的斜坡上没有一点食物
and there's no food on these nursery slopes.
海面上的冰层依然坚固
The sea ice still holds firm,
但是这种情况不会持续太久
but it won't last much longer.
第10天
Day 10,
母熊已经带领幼熊离巢1英里远
and the mother has led her cubs a mile from the den.
现在该是考验它们的时候了
It's time to put them to the test.
它们的信心日益膨胀
They've grown enormously in confidence,
不过它们并不像母熊那样着急
but they don't have their mother's sense of urgency.
最后 它们似乎做好了旅行的准备
At last it seems that they're ready for their journey
它们刚好赶得及
and they're only just in time,
离岸几英里远的海面上  冰层已经开始崩裂
for a few miles from the coast the ice is already splitting.
现在母熊将猎杀海豹  获取紧需的食物
Now the mother can start hunting for the seals they must have,
而它也正带着熊崽们 进入一个危险的新世界
but she's leading her cubs into a dangerous new world.
大约有近一半的幼熊 会在第一年的冰上历险中丧生
Nearly half of all cubs die in their first year out on the ice.
夏季意味着全天24小时的日照
Summer brings 24 hours of sunlight
融化的冰雪不断改变着地貌
and the thawing shifting landscape.
在更远的北极苔原上  冬雪几乎已经完全消失
Further south the winter snows have almost cleared from the Arctic tundra.
这里是加拿大北部荒野
Northern Canada's wild frontier.
大自然正在此上演着一幕最壮观的演出
Here nature stages one of her greatest dramas -
每年 300万迁徙的北美驯鹿 都将穿越北极苔原
Every year three million caribou migrate across the Arctic tundra.
庞大的鹿群只有在空中 才能完全领略它的壮观
The immensity of the herd can only be properly appreciated from the air.
有的鹿群一年得走上2000多英里  才能到达新鲜草场
Some herds travel over 2,000 miles a year in search of fresh pastures.
这是动物界中最长的陆地迁徙
This is the longest overland migration made by any animal.
它们总是不停地赶路
They're constantly on the move.
新生的小鹿必须 在出生的第一天就站起来奔跑
Newborn calves have to be up and running the day they are born.
但是庞大的鹿群并非独自旅行
But the vast herds do not travel alone.
狼
Wolves.
8～10只狼组成的小股部队 悄悄地尾随着迁徙的大军
Packs of them, eight to ten strong, shadow the migration.
它们已是饥肠辘辘
And they are hungry.
它们的目标就是新生的小鹿
It's the newly born calves that they are after.
直冲向鹿群是一种制造恐慌的战术
Running directly at the herd is a ploy to generate panic.
鹿群奔散开来
The herd breaks up
狼群便更容易锁定单个目标
and now it's easier to target an individual.
混乱中一只小鹿与它的母亲失散了
In the chaos a calf is separated from its mother.
小鹿虽然很小
The calf is young,
但如果全速奔跑起来  它仍可以比狼跑得更快
but it can outrun the wolf if only it manages to keep its footing.
这种情况下一般有两种可能
At this stage the odds are even -
一是驯鹿自己犯下错误
either the caribou will make a mistake
否则就是狼追出1英里之后选择放弃
or after a mile the wolf will give up.
现在是苔原的仲夏时节
Midsummer on the tundra
不会出现日落
and the sun does not set.
在这个高纬度地区  太阳辐射只能斜射到这片土地
At these latitudes the sun's rays are glancing
到达地面的能量很少  并不足以支持树木生长
and not enough of their energy reaches the ground to enable trees to grow.
由此往南500英里的地方 才有可能生长着树木
You'll need to travel 500 miles south from here before that is possible.
这些矮小的灌木标志着森林界线
These stunted shrubs mark the tree line -
北方森林由此开始
the beginning of the boreal forest -
这就是泰加林带
the taiga.
针叶树的针状树叶根本不能食用
The needle-shaped leaves of the conifers are virtually inedible
所以生活在这片森林里的动物非常稀少
so this forest supports very little animal life.
这是个寂静的地方
It's a silent place
雪地上没有被踩过的脚印
where the snow is unmarked by footprints.
每到北极冬季
In the Arctic winter
雪便为这片土地盖上一层广袤无边的银毯
snow forms a continuous blanket across the land.
可是随着春天渐渐从南方赶来
But as spring creeps up from the south
泰加林带也揭开了它的面纱
the taiga is unveiled.
这片环绕着地球的广大森林
This vast forest circling the globe
容纳了地球上1/3的树木
contains a third of all the trees on Earth
产生了大量氧气
and produces so much oxygen
从而改变了大气成分
it changes the composition of the atmosphere.
随着我们向南行进
As we travel south
太阳的影响力逐渐增强
so the sun's influence grows stronger
北纬50°的地方是一场重大变革的起点
and at 50 degrees of latitude a radical transformation begins.
由于有足够长的夏季  阔叶林得以取代针叶林
Summers here are long enough for broadleaf trees to replace conifers.
阔叶树的树叶更容易食用和消化
Broadleaves are much easier to eat and digest
因此动物们也能获得 太阳馈赠给它们的那部分能量
so now animals can collect their share of the energy that has come from the sun.
现在是夏天
It's summer
森林中一片生机勃勃的景象
and these forests are bustling with life.
可是好景不长
But the good times will not last.
由于严寒的原因 阔叶树得在冬天落叶
Broad leaves must be shed in winter for their damage by frost.
树叶消失之后
As they disappear,
大地一片荒凉 动物们的食物日益稀少
so the land becomes barren with little for animals to eat.
居民们只得迁往他处
The inhabitants must migrate,
或者冬眠
hibernate,
或者忍受几个月的饥荒
or face months of near starvation.
这是远东豹
The Amur leopard -
世界上最稀有的猫科动物
the rarest cat in the world.
这里是俄罗斯东部的落叶林
Here, in the deciduous forests of eastern Russia
冬天使得狩猎变得相当困难
the winter makes hunting very difficult.
猎物非常稀少
Pray animals are scarce,
也没有可以隐蔽的植被
and there's no concealing vegetation.
小豹已有一岁大了 仍旧依靠着它的母亲
The cub is a year old and still dependent on its mother.
鹿经常会死于严酷的冬天
Deer are frequent casualties of the harsh winter
这些豹子不会介意吃死鹿的肉充饥
and these leopards are not above scavenging from a corpse.
非洲豹根本不能在这里生存
African leopards could never survive here,
而俄罗斯的猫科动物则有厚实的皮毛 帮助它们抵挡严寒
but the Russian cats have thick fur to shield them from the cold.
如今世界上只存活着40只远东豹
There are only forty Amur leopards left in the wild
而且这个数目还在减少
and that number is falling.
与许多动物一样
Like so many creatures,
由于盗猎和栖息地遭到破坏  这些大猫已经被推到了灭绝的边缘
the cats have been pushed to the very edge of extinction by hunting and the destruction of their habitat.
远东豹充分暴露了自然遗产的脆弱
The Amur leopard symbolises the fragility of our natural heritage.
整个物种的未来寄托在 为数不多的几只母豹身上 就好比这一只
The future of an entire species hangs on survival of a tiny number of mothers like this one.
所有动物 无论稀有的还是常见的
All animals, rare or common,
归根结底都依赖于太阳的能量
ultimately depend for their energy on the sun.
在日本 每到樱花盛开的时节
In Japan the arrival of the cherry blossom
也意味着春天的来临
announces the beginning of spring.
太阳用能量创作了一幅色彩艳丽的山水画
The sun's energy brings colour to the landscape.
地球每年绕着太阳公转
The earth, as it makes its annual journey around the sun,
同时也绕着一根倾斜的轴自转
spins on a tilted axis.
正是这种倾斜造成了季节变化
And it's this tilt that creates the seasons.
世间万物随着季节的变迁不断改变
The advance of the seasons brings constant change.
在北方 随着太阳影响力的减弱
As the sun's influence diminishes in the north,
美洲落叶林开始放慢生命的脚步
so the deciduous forests of America begin to shut down
它们落下树叶 以应对 即将到来的几个月的严寒和黑暗
losing their leaves in preparation for the dark cold months ahead.
一个季节接替另一个季节
One season hands over to another.
有的生物在腐败中获得兴盛
Some organisms thrive on decay,
而更多的却得专门为冬天做好准备  以度过缺少阳光的日子
but most must make special preparations for winter and a life with little sun.
动物们成群结队踏上 寻找食物和温暖的长途旅程
Whole populations of animals are now forced to travel great distances in pursuit of food and warmth.
30万只花脸鸭集体迁往南方的韩国  躲避西伯利亚的严冬
300,000 Baikal teal gather to escape from the Siberian winter by migrating south to Korea -
仅这一群便集中了世界上所有的花脸鸭
the world's entire population in a single flock.
但是 世界上有些地方却没有四季
But there are parts of the world that have no seasons.
在热带地区 太阳辐射直射大地
In the tropics the sun's rays strike the earth head on
全年始终或多或少地 受到这种影响力的控制
and their strength is more or less constant all year round.
因此 这里的丛林茂密葱郁
That is why the jungle grows so vigourously
生命在此欣欣向荣
and supports so much life.
这些森林仅覆盖了地球表面的3%
This forest covers only 3 percent of the planet's surface,
但其中的动植物种类却占到了全球的50%
but it contains more than 50 percent of all its plants and animals.
树冠层是生命最繁荣的地方
The canopy is particularly rich.
这里有猴子、鸟
There are monkeys, birds
还有数百万种昆虫
and millions of species of insects,
至于确切数量我们不得而知
exactly how many we have no idea.
从上到下 森林的特点也在发生改变
The character of the forest changes as we descend,
越往下就越阴暗潮湿
becoming ever darker and damper,
适合各种不同种类的动植物
favouring different kinds of animals and plants.
只有不到2%的阳光能够到达丛林地表
Less than 2 percent of the sunlight reaches the floor,
即便如此 这里的生物种类也异常丰富
but even here there is extraordinary variety.
在新几内亚岛上生活着42种不同的极乐鸟
In the great island of New Guinea there are 42 different species of birds of paradise,
一种比一种奇异
each more bizarre than the last.
这片森林异常富饶
This forest is so rich
营养美味的食物唾手可得
that nourishing food can be gathered very quickly.
这也使得雄六羽极乐鸟 有时间去关心其它的事
That leaves the male six-plumed bird of paradise with time to concentrate on other matters
比如打扫它的「舞台」
like tidying up his display area.
整块地方必须干净整洁
Everything must be spick and span.
万事具备
All is ready.
非常精彩
Very impressive,
可惜没有观众
but no one is watching.
华丽极乐鸟利用鸣叫吸引异性
The superb bird of paradise calls to attract a female.
它似乎更为走运
And he has more luck.
那么 接下来它该怎么做 才能获得芳心呢？
But what does he have to do to really impress her?
雌鸟退后考虑一番 准备作出决定
She retires to consider her verdict.
雄鸟不免有些沮丧
It's hard not to feel deflated
因为它已经倾尽全力 却还是没有合格
when even your best isn't good enough.
除了陆地之外 太阳也同样 影响着海洋中的生命
The sun influences life in the oceans just as it does on land.
当海浪和洋流把大量营养物质翻上 沐浴着阳光的表层海水时
Its richest parts are those where waves and currents bring fertilising nutrients
那里便成了最热闹的用餐场所
to surface waters that are bathed in sunlight.
南非好望角外的海域就有这种神奇的魔力
The seas off the Cape in South Africa have this magic recipe
而且产量还非常高
and are hugely productive.
夏季是丰产季节
Summer is the time of plenty
也是海豹的繁殖季节
and it's now that the seals start to breed.
大白鲨的突袭仅持续短短一秒左右
The strike of a great white shark lasts a mere second.
放慢40倍的画面为你呈现了 这个巨型掠食者的纯熟技巧与强悍力量
Slowing it down forty times reveals the technique and immense strength of this massive predator.
一旦突袭失败
If surprise fails,
鲨鱼就会展开追击
there will be a chase.
鲨鱼的直线速度更快
The shark is faster on a straight course
但是转向却不如海豹灵活
but it can't turn as sharply as the seal,
这是敏捷与力量的对抗
its agility versus power.
等到海豹结束繁殖
Once the seals have finished breeding
大白鲨便会继续前进
the giant sharks will move on.
可以肯定的是  大白鲨长途跋涉数千英里横越大洋
It's now becoming clear that great whites migrate thousands of miles across the oceans
就是为了在不同海域 享用这种季节性的盛宴
to harvest seasonal abundances in different seas.
太阳烘晒着热带地区的海水
The sun, beating down on tropical waters,
驱动了全球天气系统
powers the weather systems of the globe.
海水受热蒸发成水蒸气
Moisture evaporates from the warming ocean
上升并形成巨大的风暴
and rises to create great storms.
风在外海形成
The winds generated out at sea
侵入大陆席卷内陆地区
sweep inland across the continents.
它们穿越撒哈拉沙漠时
As they travel across the Sahara
造成了世界上最大的沙尘暴
they create the biggest of all sand storms
沙子被吹到地球的另一头
blowing sand halfway round the world
亚马逊丛林因此而变得肥沃
to fertilize the Amazon jungle.
风掠过整个印度洋
Winds blowing across the Indian Ocean
一边收集水气  一边扑向北方的喜玛拉雅山脉
collect moisture and sweep northwards towards the Himalayas.
随着气流的上升 温度也逐渐下降
As the air rises, so it cools.
携带的水气开始凝结 汇集成云
The water it carries condenses into clouds
然后变成季风雨落到地面  滋润大地万物
and then falls as the life giving rains of the monsoon.
至此 由太阳驱动的大气环流
So air currents powered by the sun
将潮湿空气带到了大陆中部
carry wet air to the middle of continents.
没有水就没有生命
Without water there can be no life,
不过 水在陆地上的分配极不平均
but its distribution over the land is far from even.
沙漠覆盖了地球表面的1/3
Deserts cover one third of the land's surface
而且面积每年都在增大
and they're growing bigger every year.
这里是南部非洲的卡拉哈里沙漠
This is the Kalahari Desert in Southern Africa.
现在是旱季
It's the dry season
数千头大象开始长途跋涉  不顾一切地寻找水源
and thousands of elephants have started to travel in desperate search for water.
所有横穿南部非洲的野生动物 都怀有同样的目的
All across Southern Africa animals are journeying for the same reason.
非洲水牛也加入了这支浩大的队伍
Buffalo join the great trek.
如此多的动物出于同一个紧急目的 而进行大规模迁徙 这在地球上其它地方可看不到
Nowhere else on Earth are so many animals on the move with the same urgent purpose.
它们的目的地是奥卡万戈大沼泽
They're all heading for the swamps of the Okavango,
一片巨大的内陆三角洲
a vast inland delta.
这时它仍处于旱季
At the moment it is dry,
可是水马上就要来了
but water is coming.
肆虐的沙尘暴困住了这群迁徙的动物
The travellers are hampered by dangerous dust storms.
母象和小像一不小心就会和大部队分开
Females and calves can easily get separated from the main herd.
对于这对母子而言  避难所就在前方几英里处的林地内
For this pair sanctuary lies in the patch of woodland a few miles ahead.
它们不能休息 必须尽快到达那里
They can't rest until they reach it.
大部队早已安全抵达
The main herd has already got there safely.
最后 掉队者终于从尘埃中走了出来
Finally, the stragglers emerge from the dust.
疲惫不堪的小象仍旧看不清路  因为沙子蒙住了它的眼睛
The exhausted calf is still blinded by sand.
母象尽可能地去帮它一把
Its mother does everything possible to help it.
现在 风暴已经消退
The storm is now subsiding,
但是 并非所有的象都是那么幸运
but not all the elephants have been so lucky.
一头小象迷了路
One youngster has got lost.
尽管又渴又累
Thirsty and exhausted,
它仍追随着母亲的脚步
it follows the tracks of its mother,
不幸的是 它走错了方向
but sadly in the wrong direction.
就在卡拉哈里旱季的最高峰时
At the peak of the dry season in the Kalahari
奥卡万戈迎来了水
water arrives in the Okavango.
这些水来自数千英里外安哥拉高地的降雨
It fell as rain a thousand miles away in the highlands of Angola
奔流了将近5个月才到达这里
and has taken nearly five months to reach here.
水将燥热土壤中的昆虫驱赶出来
The water drives out insects from the parched ground,
它们很快便成了可口的点心
which are snapped up by plovers.
随着洪水一块儿到来的鲶鱼
Catfish, travelling with the flood,
捡食着那些被鸟类遗漏的溺水者
collect any drowning creatures the birds have missed.
对所有动物来说 这是一场季节性的盛宴
It's a seasonal feast for animals of all kinds.
鸟类是所有宾客中率先到达的
Birds are the first to arrive in any numbers -
肉垂鹤
wattled cranes,
接着是黑鹳
then black storks.
鸟类之后就是非洲水牛
Behind the birds come buffalo.
经过数周的长途跋涉  它们终于抵达了终点
After weeks of marching their trek is coming to an end.
洪水铺盖了奥卡万戈
As the water sweeps into the Okavango
卡拉哈里的广大地区变成了富饶的天堂
a vast area of the Kalahari is transformed into a fertile paradise.
地球上没有其它地方能比这里 更能清楚地证明水对生命的意义
Nowhere on our planet is the life giving power of water so clearly demonstrated.
动物们逐渐进入奥卡万戈的中心地带  这里的路变得纵横交错
The Okavango becomes criss-crossed with trails as animals move into its heart.
新来者开辟了新的干道  洪水流淌在这些「动脉」中 不断向外扩展
The new arrivals open up paths like arteries along which water flows, extending the reach of the flood.
这是非洲难得一见的胜景
This is an Africa rarely seen -
一个和谐繁荣的水世界
a lush water world.
有的动物干脆在这里安家
Some creatures are completely at home here.
这些是赤列羚
These are lechwe -
这种羚羊的蹄子张得很开
antelope with hooves that splay widely,
使它们能在水里快速奔走
enabling them to move its speed through the water.
而有些动物却不是很喜欢这种改变
For others the change is far less welcome.
狒狒在水里多少有些不安
Baboons are somewhat apprehensive bathers.
水为所有动物都带来了一个丰收的季节
The water brings a season of plenty for all animals.
非洲野狗
Hunting dogs.
它们现在已经成了非洲最稀有的哺乳动物
These are now among the rarest of Africa's mammals,
不过 它们仍是 非洲大陆上最有效率的掠食者
but then nonetheless the continent's most efficient predators.
它们的秘诀就是——团队协作
Their secret is teamwork.
黑斑羚是它们最喜爱的食物
Impala are their favourite prey.
捕猎行动开始
They start to hunt
狗群四下分散
and the pack splits up.
通过空中镜头  我们能从新的视角观察它们的战术
An aerial viewpoint gives a new insight into their strategy.
狗群一旦接近猎物
As the dogs approach their prey
便立刻分散 占领目标四周的各个位置
they peel off to take up separate positions around their target.
它们似乎打算对黑斑羚形成一个包围圈
They seem to form a cordon around the impala.
它们悄无声息地逼近
Moving in total silence
然后各就各位
they take up their positions.
它们的耳朵能洞悉最轻微的响声
Those ears can detect the slightest rustle.
狩猎开始
The hunt is on.
3只野狗紧追一只黑班羚
Three dogs close in on one impala.
没捉到
Missed.
头犬将黑斑羚赶向侧翼的埋伏区
The lead dog drives the impala towards the hidden flankers.
它估计了一下它们逃跑的路线
Anticipating their line
然后立刻从边角切入
the leader cuts the corner
从侧翼加入这次总攻
and joins a flanker for the final assault.
成败在此一举
It's all or nothing.
一对一
One on one.
野狗拥有耐力
The dog has stamina,
而黑斑羚拥有速度
the impala has speed.
跳入湖中是绝望的选择
Leaping into the lake is an act of desperation -
黑斑羚可不太会游泳
impala can barely swim.
野狗们知道它们的猎物迟早会上岸  否则就会淹死
The dogs know their prey must come out or drown -
现在 它们只需等待
now it's a waiting game.
狗群中的其它成员正在发出呼唤
The rest of the pack are calling.
它们已在树丛中捕到了一只猎物
They've made a kill in the forest
这是邀请它们加入宴席的信号
and this is an invitation to join in the meal.
这只黑斑羚非常走运
The impala is in luck.
这种规模的狗群每天都得进行一次捕杀 并且一起分享猎物
A pack this size kills once a day and everything is shared.
这只黑斑羚只不过被延缓了行刑的日子
And this impala is reprieved.
象群正接近漫长旅途的终点
The elephants are nearing the end of their long journey.
经过数周的长途跋涉  它们都已是精疲力尽
After weeks of marching they're desperately tired.
母象首领闻到了水的气味
The matriarch can smell water
它鼓励象群再做最后的努力
and encourages the herd to make one last effort.
小象疲惫不堪
The youngsters are exhausted
不过它们的母亲以前也经历过这种旅行
but their mothers have made this journey before
它们很清楚水就在不远的前方
and they know that they're close to water.
在完成数百英里的行程之后  它们终于抵达了目的地
After many hundreds of miles they've arrived.
这些大象的生活决定于 一年一度的干湿季节交替
The lives of these elephants are dominated by the annual rhythm of wet and dry,
这是太阳造成的季节循环
a seasonal cycle created by the sun.
在地球的最南端
At the southern end of the earth,
经历了整整4个月的黑暗后
after four months of total darkness,
太阳重新在南极上空升起
the sun once more rises over Antarctica.
现在 帝企鹅们终于不用再挤在一起了
Now at last the Emperor penguins abandon their huddle.
雄企鹅们仍然看护着它们的宝贝
The males are still carrying the precious eggs
在整个漫长的南极冬夜  它们一直呵护着自己的蛋
that they've cherished throughout the Antarctic winter.
随着太阳的回归 蛋也开始孵化
With the returning sun the eggs hatch.
其它鸟还没有到来
Other birds have not even arrived.
而帝企鹅却熬过了一个漫长黑暗的冬天
but the Emperors by enduring the long black winter
因而它们的宝宝也有了领先的优势
have given their chicks a head start.
现在 这些小家伙们已经做好准备  急切盼望着享受南极那短暂的夏天
These youngsters are now ready and eager to make the most of the brief Antarctic summer.